<d:chapter version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <!--
      Copyright (C)  2013 Shiv S. Dayal.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
      A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
      Free Documentation License".

  -->
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
  <?dbhtml filename="introduction/index.html" ?>
  <d:title> Introduction </d:title>
  <d:para>
    I do not think I need to introduce GNU/Linux to anyone remotely interested
    in computers and programming in particular. Well, exceptions are always
    there like old people who do nothing but browse, chat and email or
    possibly go to Facebook or kids who have just started working on computers.
    Some people might have heard the term Ubunut or Fedora or OpenSUSE or Mint
    or Debian etc and maybe also using them without knowing that essentially
    all are GNU/Linux variations. You would ask me what is GNU/Linux then
    because all other names mentioned previously are open source operating
    system. You might even ask I have heard of Linux what is this GNU?
    Well, GNU is an acronym which stands for "GNU is not Unix". GNU is an
    ecosystem which provides Linux as its kernel. And no GNU/Linux is not
    only an operating system but it is a complete package. For almost all needs
    you just need to install one of the distributions mentioned. GNU or free
    software movement was started by Richard Stallman in 1983. The objective
    was to provide free operating system. What did you say free means no
    price? No no it means freedom. Free as in freedom not free beer. Remember
    it and never forget because if you forget or do not respect your
    freedom you will end up loosing it. GNU was meant to provide freedom both
    to the programmers and to the users from proprietary software. You do not
    have to spend zillions of dollars to aquire the software and more importantly
    you can modify it because source code is available to you. Now note that
    you can modify it not like other proprietary system where you know there
    is a problem and you know what is the fix but you cannot apply it even
    though you have bought it. Consider you have bought a car and it is
    not working and you know you can fix it then wont you? Will the car company
    come and stop you? No, right. But in software world in the name of
    intellectual property rights money is looted from its users for second grade
    worthless software. You know what I am pointing towards. Oh how I hate you
    would say. Yes I hate and I pity them together. Is it only their knowledge
    they are building the software upon. NO! Knowledge has accumulated by the
    contribution of many people over thousands of years. We learn something
    from previous generations and we build upon it. Then on what grounds there
    can be a copyright on knowledge. It is with the same thought I write free
    books in the free spirit. I would rather live one day as free man and die
    than live hundred years of luxurious life of slavery. These companies which
    manufacture proprietary software are trying to enslave the very life.
  </d:para>
  <d:para>
    The first step which you can take is install a distribution of GNU/Linux. I
    prefer Mint because it ships with Mate as default and its green theme is
    soothing. It is just a personal perference. Ubuntu is not bad either though
    they have taken a bad approach towards secure boot. Debian and Cent OS are
    pretty solid for servers. If you are on one of the popular proprietary
    systems and afraid of doing a native install then I encourage you to watch
    my video on how to install Mint GNU/Linux on VirtualBox. You can view this
    <d:ulink
	url="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ltuKHo4UCrY">here</d:ulink>. I
    will try to make more such videos and upload them. Now go ahead and take
    your first step towards freedom by installing one of the distributions of
    GNU/Linux.
  </d:para>
  <d:para>
    Now that you have installed GNU/Linux I will tell you how to use it. We
    will start with command line and later we will see at GUI. GUI is easy
    becasue you can do a lot by yourself. If you have installed Mint with Mate
    then you have a terminal or in Ubintu you have a terminal. Note that
    underlyrng terminal is almost same but the difference is in their
    names. One is called <d:code>mate-terminal</d:code> and another is called
    <d:code>gnome-terminal</d:code>. If you have installed KDE based desktop
    manager then you would have a program called <d:code>konsole</d:code>. Just
    navigat the GUI menus to find them and start them. The menu should be at
    bottom-left or top-left. Once you are there you would see a prompt ending
    with <d:code>$</d:code>. This sgnifies you are using a bash(bourne again
    shell) as a normal user. If you are a root (the alll powerful administrator
    of a Unix or GNU/Linux system) then it would be <d:code>#</d:code>. Note
    that you can not login as root in most of these system but you can do that
    easily. I will tell you about that later. So now we have this prompt (it is
    called a prompt because it is asking you to enter a command which it is
    ready to serve for you if possible and you do not mess that). Let us see
    what we can do with this prompt.
  </d:para>
  <d:sect1>
    <d:title>Starting with Command Prompt</d:title>
    <d:para>Whatever command you enter is first word or string if it has
    spaces or some special characters. Note that if you have such special stuff
    then it has to be quoted. For now let us not worry about that and try to
    see what we have. Most of the commands will be one word or path to one file
    which must be executable. When I say executable then it means it should be
    able to execute not only in the sense of permissions. You can mark even a
    text file executable but that does not mean it will execute meanigfully.
    </d:para>
  </d:sect1>
</d:chapter>
